[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
so this will be recorded um so if
there's
anything that you don't want to say on
youtube
you can indicate in the chat that you'd
like me to read the question
for you and please feel free to plus one
other people's questions that's helpful
for uh figuring out what
is resonating with the the group so that
we
get to the pith of what we want to talk
about more easily
and quickly last but not least please
keep yourself on mute
if you have not been called on to ask
your question and so thank you
michael for joining us today thanks for
having us
yeah looking forward to speaking with
you so
uh just to kick it off kind of give a
lay of the land
wanted to get just a brief introduction
to kind of your
uh your purview of the meditation
landscape i know that you
are uh sometimes more on the secular
side of things often times you
cover various traditions marianas and
all that so
what uh what's your take on the kind of
meditation landscape right now and how
did you come to that
brief the meditation landscape right now
in regards to
yeah yeah okay i'll just
dive in and say uh this is by far the
most
interesting time in the western
meditation landscape i've ever seen by
far
sometimes things were in
some ways more exciting because there
was like a new a new teacher or new
stuff
rising up or new opportunities but that
was always in a context
of extreme uh paucity
and poverty of eddie big to engage with
um and so what makes the current moment
so
fascinating and rich and engaging and
powerful
is that
[Music]
it's all out there right every if
there's
anything you're interested in learning
you can learn it you can learn it from
10 different highly qualified people you
can learn it in different formats you
can
engage in whatever way you want to
engage there's almost nothing that
you can't find
and previously even recently but
you know i've been doing this since the
70s so you know
previously that just wasn't even
remotely possible there was
a lot of stuff you know that i had to go
to india to do
and spend long long time there to engage
with
or you know uh almost like figure out
for yourself
by reading hints in the side notes of
something so anyway this is great
it's super exciting and i feel like
it can only help i think that the
meditation landscape
has been suffering from
uh free for decades from too few people
being engaged
uh only nightmarishly obsessed weirdos
like me
being the people who are engaged like
people willing just you know give up
their whole life to do it
um and furthermore uh and most
importantly
um because we were taking on
ways of learning and ways of teaching
and ways of communicating that were
from other cultures and were often times
like
basically medieval in character um
they're the the opportunity for dialogue
and critique
and feedback and group
vetting of ideas and comparing of
notes was just not happening
it was just not available and as we know
this is one of the best things that
um we could say something like
science you know the project of science
has contributed to
the world is that whole idea of we're
all going to get in the public sphere
hanging out in a actual stoa somewhere
you know in a public meeting space and
just
uh compare notes and critique the
out of stuff and people have to defend
what they're saying you know
instead of just kind of giving the
teaching from on high and
and everybody's feedback right so
this is a great moment and i think that
it's going to
uh you know lead to a completely
new sort of dialogue in this world it
already has but
actually develop new forms of dialogue
in the meditation sphere and probably
rocket the whole fuel forward just in
time for the
human race to die so you know
i'm excited likewise
uh and what where do you see
deconstructing yourself falling in all
of this that you just described
uh is this in yourself is a website and
is blog posts and is a
uh podcast and is retreats etc etc so
it depends on which one of those you
mean but i'm
trying to do uh maybe maybe two and i'll
probably kind of spanish inquisition
three two
three number three and number four in
there also but
um essentially i'm trying to further
that dialogue
number one i really think it's a super
important dialogue
uh and at the same time i don't want to
be
the kind of like clearing house of all
dialogue
uh because i actually want to also be
teaching some stuff
also uh helping or providing a platform
for a couple other teachers
so it's sort of like minimally a teacher
platform and a dialogue platform
um and furthermore i there's
there's i have a desire to just document
what's going on that's
i like to have conversations with
teachers just because
to me it's personally
fascinating you know they're interesting
what they're doing is interesting what
they're thinking is interesting
so uh that was number three i told you
i'd do that
um and there's probably a few more but
that's that's where i see deconstructing
yourself uh
landing you know it's the venn diagram
covers a lot
um since in-person retreats aren't
happening
um that's a bummer i love traveling for
in-person retreats and seeing folks and
engaging in that kind of
alembic uh sort of pressure cooker
environment of a of a retreat
uh but since that is not happening uh
i'm doing
online courses now and so that's that's
that's new right like zoom course that's
really fascinating and providing
i think new opportunities for people to
learn but also new opportunities for me
to figure out how to
present the material i want to present
so deconstructing yourself is kind of a
umbrella term for a gigantic field of
stuff
all to do with basically meditation
spirituality getting to know yourself
befriending your mind
connecting with other humans on a in a
very deep way
etc great thanks
uh and just as he as michael talks feel
free to throw questions in the chat
uh i'll keep going until i see some
coming up so
michael everybody cares yeah
i care that's all that matters so uh
the opportunity to drink more teas yeah
that's right
excellent fun so uh
within that i mean you've done a broad
survey
of a variety of practices you've
practiced in a
variety of traditions yourself right now
we find ourselves in kind of a
liminal space especially in the in the
united states
uh which where we are both located
and what sort of practices are most
alive for you right now both as a
as an individual practitioner and as a
teacher for helping you
navigate through the the variety of
things that we're faced with in this
world
you know i in a way uh
i'll answer your question in two
different ways at least maybe three or
four
but in a way i would say
what's most interesting to me is
whatever practice helps the individual
the most
so something that this time frame
and also just my personal journey is
making possible right now
is um to do
individual fitting of practices
to people and um
it turns out that that is a that it's a
lot more individual than you might think
you know a huge part of my daily life
what i do every day is talk to people
one-on-one i do one-on-one
meditation coaching hours and hours and
hours a day and am i doing this for
many many many years and one of the main
things i've learned from that actually
that
i've learned so much from that it's an
incredible
gift i feel really really honored to be
able to do that
but one of the big things i've learned
is just how
utterly different people's minds
actually
are because i'm talking to them
one-on-one
and then talking about their practice
and then getting into the details of
their practice and how they relate to it
and
what's working and what's not working
and what you realize
is you know there is no
one-size-fits-all
and not even kind of i mean it's hard to
even
i can do it but it's hard to even group
people into
major categories it's more like okay
what have you already done
where is the opening happening for you
so to me
i would say the actually the most
fascinating thing
is that we have an opportunity to get in
there and
you know make bespoke
versions of practices for everyone and i
think that's
actually one of the first times we can
do this at a at a bigger
scale and that that's what's actually
required right now
it was back in the kind of 70s and 80s
that it was like let's
pack 300 people in this meditation hall
and just tell them to watch their prep
and then see what happens you know it's
all going to go
well because it's so easy you know those
days are gone
hopefully forever and
we're leaning in i'm leaning into more
and more
individual uh type stuff so that's
the first part of the answer the the
second part of the answer is
um right now um
there is i think um
boy it's a complicated question it's
really
uh thank you for asking interesting
questions i would say that um
we can take sort of a route that goes
out of
um really uh summit to focus
practices especially show it to with an
object and we can take a route out of
practices that begin with shamatha
without an object
and of course we can actually stack
those two routes depending on the person
those are very very interesting to me
right now
and then the third thing would be the
third big category would just be
everything that i would roughly throw in
a pile called
compassion practice or not to practice
so
um you know i don't specialize or work
that much
in a sort of group process practices
i think those are fascinating that's
just not my background but i'm glad that
people are
doing that meaning you know more dia
type practice or
or live everyone talking to each other
in a group type practice
of course meditating together in a group
we've always done
awesome thanks so much for that i think
that that leads nicely
into david has a question about the
the differences in trainings around
shamatha and jhana practices so
david if you'd like to unmute yourself
and ask that
hi michael i recently saw your how to
johnna
instructions and um was struck
by one how powerful
such experience can be and beneficial
and two how different that presentation
was
from the instruction i received um
i worked with uh shyla catherine a uh
student of barack sandow
and you may know powek's instructions
are
exhaustingly precise you know
identifying 24 dharmas in each third of
a second
sort of thing but the basic rupa jhana
procedure she outlines works with the
animator arises on its own
but you stay with the nematode and
things unfold that way
i heard a different focus in your
approach
having a meditation focus an object but
attending to the pt's particularly as it
manifests
somatically um i'm reminded
and i'll i'll be real brief of a stroke
of jesus scholar
noticing when you hear someone say
is this not the most beautiful baby in
the world
that the indefinite article has gone to
definite
how often powerful transformative
wholesome practices are so
uh eminently valuable that we tend to
understand that is the way to
that it's done so i'm interested in sort
of a general
outlook you might have on differences
in approaches to to what ended up being
powerfully wholesome
practice instructions yeah thanks david
you know the thing with the jhanas
is that the way they are originally
described
in the pseudos by the buddha
they are one-dimensional right we
especially the rupa-janas we proceed
one through four in a sequence that's it
it's a one-dimensional scale
and that scale has various uh
each notch on that scale has various
qualities
okay um but what
has happened over time is that
various meditation traditions have
introduced a second dimension
into the diagram without actually ever
admitting they're doing that and so
at each of those notches of the rupa
jhanas one two three four
there's now a dimension of depth okay
so it you know we had previously each
one of the genres had
its described qualities
and you were going deeper along a
sequence and that sequence could be
described as greater refinement
of the meditation object but now
over the thousands of years a dimension
has
of depth has been added and when you're
talking about paul outsider or shayla
catherine
or john brahm or several other teachers
they're always only talking about the
absolutely deepest depth
of jhana which is something that was
introduced a thousand years after the
buddha
and also which is only available
to a small portion of practitioners even
ones who are
and i'm talking about a small portion of
people who are
uh um in complete
lockdown retreat so in other words even
if a hundred people go into complete
lockdown retreat
to do that level of john only a few of
them will ever be able to do it
this is nothing like what is presented
by the buddha in the sutures right it's
a much lighter genre that he's talking
about
and you can prove it through various you
know you go in there and talk about
you pick apart the descriptions and some
of these things aren't possible
at all if you're at this deepest level
um of janna and so what i'm presenting
uh in the how to jonna video which is
just you know
a very brief give it a shot like this
kind of instructional video
is a medium level genre that's not even
the lightest
level that you could do like the
lightest level that say chula dasa talks
about in the tmi book where it's
even barely there at all but this is
the what i'm describing is what we would
also
call the lee brazington of jhana which
is kind of medium
and uh it's just not that hard to do
for a lot of people like i said for um
[Music]
it's meditation is practices are so
individual that there's plenty
of people who won't be able to do it but
what i've discovered is
for the kind of person who gets
quote body energy when you focus you
know
some kind of buzzy tingly pleasant
energy in your body when you focus which
turns out to be a lot of people
then going into this medium level of
janna is
very very easy um
and i what i found out there was that
there was
not many good descriptions of that and a
lot of the descriptions were hard to
find or overly complex or
arcane in lots of ways so
it's my one of my joys in life is just
saying
look here's how to do this it's not that
hard in making it as simple as possible
um and there was a whole other bunch of
stuff in there like people getting very
complex about what pt means and what
suka means
it's just not that hard i'm sorry you
know it's much more direct and simple
the other thing i would say is that and
if you can get into that medium level
john i'm describing
um you may be one of the people who then
starts noticing when you're in that
genre a big nematode comes up
that happens for me you know you sit
down you're doing the jhana
you're going in at a medium level but
you're there for just a few moments
under
big nimitz comes up now
you have access to even that deeper
level
that people like shiloh catherine are
talking about
um so it's not somehow an inferior
or a lesser or a useless thing it's
actually a
fabulous step for almost you know
whether you want to do vapasana next
whether you want to go into some kind of
open awareness next whatever
if you're able to get into even a medium
level first second
third john is something like that it's a
great stepping stone
so i love them uh and i think that
they are sort of unfairly uh
confined to just tarabata buddhism
and they don't need to be and uh
furthermore the sort of jhana wars which
all come about
by um you know people not
understanding that there's this second
dimension of depth are just unnecessary
it's like well start out at the easy
level and gradually you'll go to the
next level
you know it's just not that hard
thanks that's helpful
thanks david i saw a few plus ones on
scott's question
he asked me to read it so scott would be
curious to hear you comment on how
you're training with
shinzen's method connects with your
interest in non-dual practices
like the lock kelly interviews that you
did recently
well even in the shinzon interviews
where me and shinzo are talking about na
dual stuff
um you know the thing that people
don't realize about shinzon is that he's
not a vibasana teacher
and that's easy to mistake
because he constantly calls himself of a
passionate teacher
and so i don't believe andy bled for
getting that
incorrect but it's um
you know he spent his first five years
as in shin gong practice which is
you know japanese vadriana right and
then
he spent as a monk so he was doing
japanese vajrayana for five years
then uh started doing zen with sasaki
roshi's
and you know for like 30 years or
something
and so if you really had to categorize
him
i would categorize him as a three
vehicle teacher who's using like a very
non-dual view
to teach uh dualistic vipassana
or seemingly dualistic vipassana that
then kind of
gradually moves into a non-dual version
that
but you know if you had to describe him
in a nutshell
i would say he's actually a zen teacher
who's just really committed to
being really clear in a way that zen
teachers are
never clear um so if you ask him a
question you know instead of sort of
yelling at you
or saying something enigmatic
or taking a sip of tea and of course i'm
kind of joking here but he
um you know he'll take the time to just
elaborately explain it to you
um and so he's a zen guy who
who just likes that the the
sort of model of vipassana gives him a
way to
talk about stuff in a really kind of
structural way
but from the very beginning he's always
pushing you into non-dual view
over and over and over and over and over
and over and over so
um shinzon students who become teachers
have this
weird uh way of
describing stuff really dualistically
and then pushing people into
non-dualistic
module type experiences so
um and it happens
like after i had worked with shinzon for
a long time i kept i really
liked meditating on what we would call
flow in i would call it flow in thinking
so
you know you're you're watching
impermanence in the mind in a very very
clear way but the more i did that
um and of course this was not like me
as a subject watching the mind as an
object over there it's very
non-dual version of this where we would
say it's
slightly previous to non-dual it would
be kind of a lottong or
you know non-dualish vipassana method
but the um the net result was like
i i thought i had invented an entirely
new field of meditation i'm like oh my
god this is just completely fascinating
and i'm unpacking all this crazy stuff
about the mind and i'm
writing all of it down and then one day
i'm like you know this is just
mahamudra like it's absolutely not
different in any way for mahamudra
and it's just he never uses the word
mahamudra you know and so
it's like it took me a while to realize
that
what we were doing was quite different
actually than the pasta
so that's a long long long description
to say
it connects perfectly well with non-dual
practices
in in every possible way and it's
actually just
um the fact that previously he didn't
talk very much about
um
let's say awareness of awareness
practices even though that's how he
actually
had his initial awakening that's all his
initial training that's
all his zen training etc etc he
preferred to come
in through the vipassana kind of view at
first
[Music]
and so over time now he teaches
that as well he's he's always been
teaching do nothing but now he's got a
whole you know
he's integrating it even more completely
i think maybe based on student interest
but also
based on the fact that a bunch of people
like me
who um you know have started teaching
from his background are integrating that
much more
in the front and much more uh
consciously
and with now uh with more
uh informed background
does that answer your question i'm not
sure if that was even what you were
asking but that's how it integrates for
me
yeah scott's scott's microphone isn't
working he wrote me in the chat so i
don't think that he can respond
unfortunately unless you want to chat
like with a follow-up scott
uh so evan uh do you want to unmute
yourself and ask your question
sure thanks hi michael i absolutely love
your
podcast and everything you do it's one
of the highlights of my
day when a new one drops so thank you
for that and then i wanted to ask you a
question
about it thanks evan i want to interrupt
and say you've got some um
visionary art on the wall behind you who
is that by
um i think it's uh mugwort
is the artist's name
nice yeah my you know my wife is a
visionary artist and works with alex
gray all the time and stuff so i
i'm like i recognize that from somewhere
so my question is um in regards to uh
it's kind of a complicated question but
i guess so you know i've been doing this
for a long time
and i had some very brief forays into
taking on a sort of
formal teacher role and found that went
very badly um
and uh and so i've stepped way back from
that for the past 15 years or so and i
see
um i see a lot of my friends and
acquaintances who have sort of gone the
teacher
route within the domains of meditation
spirituality yoga etc
um being really vulnerable to what i
would call
market forces right so whether this is
you know you have to change the emphasis
of your teaching in order to
to get more followers subscribers
students
you have to change your uh presentation
you have to do a lot of what seems to me
like frankly really aggressively
self-promoting
type activity or at least most people
who go this route seem to kind of end up
in that pickle
and i see a lot of a lot of sort of
distortion happening
maybe with what people are really into
versus what they work with publicly
because of these sort of market forces
so just maybe hoping you could riff on
that dynamic of like
obviously we have a very different model
for how teachers are compensated
and most of the traditional cultures
from which these practices are derived
and
and maybe just talk about that dynamic
in our society and your thoughts about
it and
especially any thoughts on how to engage
with teaching and not be captured by
those dynamics
thank you yeah nothing to say about any
of that
tiny topic
hang on
i sort of alluded to one of the first
things earlier which is
um we have this idea
that you want to get like 300 people in
a hall
and then just give them a technique and
one size fits all and it's sort of the
production line kind of model of
capitalism
and you know that might actually work
a little bit for basic practices it
might work
in a way for apps for basic practices
like okay here's the minimum version of
just paying attention to your breath at
all
or you know doing some
uh do nothing at all or whatever like
sometimes the basic instructions are so
simple
and maybe people will get a lot out of
it but i don't know
uh the um
the kind of like
gigantic stadium model of meditation
teaching is just not
where i'm at i don't like it
um i i don't think it does
very much if anything and so
that whole idea of marketing that's like
you want as many as possible
is just as far as i'm concerned
literally
the wrong idea but i'll i'll back off
and say
probably the wrong idea most of the time
um instead and when i see teachers do
that
i i just hold my head in my hands
because it's like
you're not going to like the outcome
teacher and the students aren't going to
like the outcome
nobody's going to be happier you know
a friend of mine who is a spiritual
teacher uh
thought it would be a cool idea i mean
it was a cool idea i like
you know uh experiments so
this person like did a uh
you know monthly payment group that was
like you know we were gonna
uh you spend a certain amount each month
to just get online and kind of ama the
crap out of him
and and you know there's like 700 people
in that group or something
and it's just it's just trolls
and chaos and griefers and stuff
and so you know nobody i'm positive
he didn't get what he wanted out of it
he despises it and
you know is desperately calling for
something you know a different model
and i'm pretty sure the people didn't
like it either
um and
[Music]
what i have found works is
um boutique you know
it's like do exactly what you
actually do as a teacher be into
what you're exactly into the way you're
into it with all the weird little
niches and create you know every little
detail of how you like it
and then present that and do it to a
very small number of people who are
deeply
deeply deeply into that
and then you know
you're going to be happy with what
you're doing and they're going to be
happy with what you're doing
and it's um
[Music]
we're all set up for it now i mean you
know the
technological tools make this really
really really easy
and it's actually in a strange way
going back to something much more
traditional
where there were here's your specific
teacher
and they've got a small group of
students sitting around them
at the stoa or whatever you know in in
in athens or wherever was it in athens
um you know hanging out
and you know you're just interacting
with
one at a time or a small group of people
it's real
real eye contact you
you and it's like a transmission you
know and i don't mean that in the
mystical sense
when i was at university when i would
find
professors that i liked i would just
sign up for every course they taught no
matter what the
course was because it was just about
that interaction with that
teacher and and
that's very traditional in the
meditation world and it's also
traditional that you then do that
um with various teachers you learn for a
while with one in this very close way
until you're ready to move on and then
you and it's there's nothing
there's no big deal about it it's like
oh you're gonna go get that teaching
from that other teacher who specializes
in that thing
you know so i think there's this other
kind of model possible
it's the model i'm doing you know i try
to do everything as small as possible
with as much contact as possible because
a i think that gets the best results for
everyone and b
um we can do it now
you know it's just so easy
and i think we're developing new
teaching
models you know like a kind of practice
group
like let's say evolving ground or
whatever where
it is larger but it's not it's people
talking you know and
and then having the possibility of
interacting
uh more one-on-one so there's a lot
going on here
and i think you you know
wherever you go you find the forces of
capitalism trying to
rape the out of everything and
destroy anything good about it
and just flatten it into
a deracinated and entirely
uh
nutrition free pancake of doom and
uh it just blows my mind how fast
teachers die for that and they're like
you know i want a million students each
at
seven dollars a month and then it's just
uh um i couldn't
think of something worse to happen with
spirituality
on the other hand maybe that's great for
some people
so if they're enjoying that fine go for
it but
i just keep moving toward towards this
other end and i think
um i think part of why it's happening
is that and this is just my personal
uh judgment maybe i'm wrong i'm
super open to being completely wrong
because i am all the time
um i think part of this is
people jumping into teaching too soon
you know before they really have a lot
of experience and a lot to share
um and that's fine jump in soon there's
i'm not even saying you shouldn't do
that but when
when you're still kind of teaching at
the
more or less basic level it might feel
like you want you know
you don't have the it might feel like
that sort of um
low impact big crowd thing
fits better i don't know maybe maybe
that's not what people are thinking
uh anyway i could go on about this topic
for a long long time
because it's fascinating but
i'll end there for now having any
follow-ups
no i appreciate that very much i uh good
perspective and very useful thank you
i think that this actually dovetails
very nicely with rob's question
uh talking about the varieties of
teachers and the varieties of practices
so rob if you want to
unmute yourself sure yeah so i've been
dabbling for the last few years in
different meditation practices that i've
learned from various books and teachers
and i'm
glad to have a variety of practices and
i i really respect that you
blend a variety in your work and the
question for me is this has actually
been a challenge in meditation that i
have a variety of practices now i sit
and when something arises
there's like a choice to make about
which practice to follow or which
recommendation to use or if i'm not
already committed from start like
what am i gonna do now that i've got
something arising so
um so the question becomes you know not
what do i do about that but do you have
a rubric you use to sort of tell you how
you
blend these practices together sort of a
meta practice awareness that says which
practices are going to be useful and for
what purposes
well yeah absolutely uh but
not one that is correct or the same for
everybody so the idea is
let's go in and look at what you've
learned and figure out how to make a
decision tree that
you know allows you to you know kind of
optimize that for what's coming up
um right
so uh you it shouldn't be the case
um or let me put a different way i can
see why that would be frustrating right
like you're sort of like
i don't know what to do here but the
idea
is you probably do know what to do
you're just not sure when to apply it
and so we just want to go through and
look at
your stack and see how to arrange it
into a thing that makes sense
um maybe that answer is frustrating
because i'm not
actually giving you something you could
use
so i will say that
for most people most of the time you
want to have your basic practice
that you do every day and this is what
you're working on
and that's your edge and that's what
you're you know developing and unfolding
and growing that's where you're doing
the growth and then you have one or two
um variety pack practices
that you do on some days just to keep
yourself from going
insane from boredom or whatever and so
they're just
interesting helpful fun
[Music]
cross training type practices
and then you have let's say
i'll just say a small amount two or
three at the most
sort of like um practices that you bring
in for specific difficult stuff that
sometimes arises
and you may have you may have learned a
lot more than that
but i would narrow it down to like
here's the main thing i'm working on
right now
not necessarily for the rest of my life
but what about for the next six months
i'm
doing this one practice and then my
variety practices this other thing i do
it two times a week
but when let's say some really difficult
uh emotional material comes up and i'm
it's it's really disrupting the main
practice
so much that um i need to do something
about it
then i then i use this other practice
that is specifically works for that
so that kind of thing you know that
would be
that's the sort of stack you wanted to
develop so that
you know what to do
and then over time in the grandiose
scale so
every six months you're reevaluating
that what's the next
practice for six months that i'm really
working on
right so it shouldn't be the case that
every single day it's like what am i
gonna do
you know but you've got one main one
mainstream you're moving forward
okay and in my way of looking at it
no one can really tell you what that
should be
you know that's that's your own
choice but if you have uh
something that you're you know
fascinated by interested in want to
feel like you could really get something
out of feel like you have got a lot out
of and want to grow more with and that's
your base practice right now
if you want to tell me more about what
you're actually doing i can go into it
but maybe that's not the best
use of the whole group's time maybe as a
demo
otherwise i'll just give you the general
version there
actually i think i prefer the general
version because it feels more broadly
applicable to like
what i might change about in the future
so thank you yeah of course
thanks for asking
awesome uh alf
would you like to ask your question
please hey elf
how's it going dude what's up michael uh
what country are you in right now
uh still in upstate new york uh pandemic
is sidelining
me personal problems but
uh appreciate your pragmatic uh advice
there to rob
uh my question uh a little bit more
philosophical
but uh kind of dealing with what you're
talking about with new evolving teacher
dynamics
but in the sense-making and
meaning-making crisis and god knows what
else is going on right now
uh you know we've heard some talk about
the next buddha being the sangha
and i was just curious of your thoughts
on that we're starting to see some of
that emergence in communities like stowa
and other places where
the internet's kind of representing what
it was intended to be but
i'm just curious if you have a view on
that i know friends like vince have
different
non-teacher dynamics as well
yeah so the person who said that was
tikna han right he
busted that out in the 90s it's not
actually a new statement
and technolon's a great teacher right i
mean you got to respect the guy he's out
there in
in rural villages in vietnam uh
attempting to be killed by both
uh the americans and the north
vietnamese while he was
he and his monks were and nuns were
rebuilding villages um
you know nominated for a nobel peace
prize by martin luther king
technology is a fascinating human and
so he said that and who am i to
gain say it or nay say it but i would
say that
um you know he's definitely onto
something there
and it's part of what i was pointing to
in my opening remarks or whatever where
i was saying that
the discussion part and the student
discussion
and the sort of open teacher discussions
i mean
nothing is more forbidden in traditional
meditation groups than people
asking the teacher why they're saying
what they're saying or
you know justifying it or comparing it
to another technique or
you know that is like forboden right
this is just
not okay uh traditionally and so
i should say and
uh it's a wonderful thing that now we
have this opportunity to just
ask whatever
and talk about the answer and see what
we think and then
work with work with in whatever
direction
we think is most positive or
most likely to be positive so in other
words what i'm saying is i think that
that
it's you're right it's already happening
and it's just gotta happen a lot more
it's part of what i'm trying to do on
the podcast
is take all these teachers and just
talk to them basically like a person
you know like not as a teacher who
you can't ask these really personal
questions about this stuff
um and i could probably do that more
forcefully but
uh it's not about like jamming it open
or getting in there to get some dirt or
something
it's just more about let's open this
up and because
you know what's been the new meditation
technique in the last
thousand years tell me
you know answer there isn't one
you know not really uh we can say maybe
the headless way or something but
there's certainly stuff
from the past you can interpret that way
um
there just isn't one and why isn't there
one because
uh the last groups of
people really discussing in the open
and critiquing and evaluating and trying
stuff out experimentally
instead of just taking it as the
received you know like
truth died out a thousand years ago
i mean not totally of course but there
just hasn't been that much new stuff i
would say
i'm exaggerating a little bit but not
much
and so hopefully now you know we
have what does it take to do
a lot of experiments in a lot of
directions it takes a big group
of people who are all experimenting and
all talking about their results in a
very open way
so if we're calling that a sangha then
yes
the next buddha the next phase of us
really really
learning and growing and getting better
at this
is not just one group it's
it's like all the groups together and
everyone talking and interacting
in publishing and all that
and then there's a couple people i see
at least one
neuroscientist in this group
and so then we add in even another
factor
the you know like
objective view of all this which
has almost never been there at all in
the past
and we see you know shenzhen's down
there locked in a lab with jay
sanguinetti like
zapping his brain with uh you know
neutron bombs a couple times a day and
seeing what happens and
before kovit inviting anyone to show up
and get their brains out
you know this is this is even beyond the
next buddhist sangha idea and let's say
the next buddha is a sangha
and you know some some
equipment so i think
uh we are and of course i mean i'm very
very aware
of all the ways that can go horribly
wrong like let's analyze poetry using
our
you know like uh computer and so on
you know there's ways that we can take
what's really going on with this thing
uh called meditation and called human
spirituality and just
smash and to just
uh reduce the out of it until it's
nothing
and i'm not into that of course but i do
think that you know combining these
elements we may be
seeing the possibility of a
creative flowering golden age you know
um of meditation like we've never seen
so that's yeah hoping
let's see i like doing
that one um but we'll do
that one so oh here's hoping
thanks awesome
let's end with a doozy uh aslam
would you like to i hope i pronounced
your name right would you like to unmute
yourself please
oh come on let's have a doozy i'm
waiting yeah
i'm sorry i did not mean uh
it's maybe not great the way that i've
uh asked but i was just
uh wondering if you could
give us the description of
a disc uh deconstructed
self and uh and if you
feel that uh you've reached a level that
you could just sense that
you're deconstructed yourself
or closer to it the way that
you think about it and
maybe you could share your practices and
what's next
for you uh as an example first to
learn from your experience how much time
we got
yeah so you know one of the most
interesting
uh ideas uh is the idea that the self
is somehow unitary whole
singular or even there at all
um and we know that this is not just
you know a western conceit or
a late capitalistic idea or something
that's been around for a long time it's
kind of a natural idea me
but something that it becomes
clear in meditation
very quickly is what we're calling me
[Music]
can change can depend
uh and can show up in a whole bunch of
different ways
can not show up at all and this
just comes from the simple act of
looking within
um whatever that means to you i'll just
use the vagus possible
idea of meditation as you say looking
within
if you do that for a little while you'll
notice
different voices are talking there's
different
goals for different voices talking
you know there's um conflicting
urges happening in there who are they
conflicting between
um sometimes there's no
talking at all sometimes there doesn't
even seem to be a viewpoint at all
sometimes you know i could just go on
and on
and so even with the most cursory
we could do a five minute meditation
here and you've net let's say you've
never meditated a moment in your life i
could still demonstrate that the idea
of a self becomes very unitary
continuously present
individual unique self because that is
you know one thing is immediately
questionable and
it's only a like a
social construct basically that we have
this one self that's always the same
and that is even there at all
um and so
[Music]
you know hell yes i feel
deconstructed all the time in one way of
talking about it
and that's good you know
um because if if you're unaware
of this basic level of multiplicity
of cells we could call them sub
personalities or whatever within you
or unaware of the fact that sometimes
even all of those are in abandons
and there's just seems to be this
beautiful open space with nothing
particularly happening in it
um if you're unaware of how all of that
changes
contextually when in relationship with
other humans
when you know interacting with other
beings animals etc
[Music]
if one is unaware of all that one is not
only
you know not paying attention but also
really missing out on something really
interesting about humans
and so it's a it's not
hard it's a fundamental thing to notice
that this i
you know if i were to say the title a
little differently i would say
deconstructing the idea of a self
you know because there isn't really a
singular self there to even deconstruct
um but the uh
looking at in your own experience
what constitutes moment by moment
right now the thing that you're calling
me if in fact you are calling anything
me
and what that looks like when you just
either allow it to arise in awareness
and just be with it
or kind of look at
individual parts more clearly
if you do that that's going to be really
really interesting
and really powerful and start to change
your whole idea
of what who you are who other people are
and what it even means to be a human
being
and i think there are several different
directions that
we can go and and uh one of them is
well even though i have a sense of self
there is no self there at all
in terms of the um
or let's say any self that seems to be
there is
you know just some constructed activity
and that the closer to the actual self
thing is just open awareness
although even that's empty but we can
also go in another direction which is
equally fascinating and equally
traditional
which is multiple cells you know like
well actually there's
all these different sort of what we
might call sub personalities they're all
constructions
on top of emptiness on top of awareness
you know um that beca and let's start
negotiating with those or even creating
new interesting ones or whatever
just kind of the tantric direction
and tantrism arises out of indian
shamanism and tibetan shamanism and so
on so it's
very traditional really goes back a long
way so
all of these different things are things
i'm pointing at
with this basic term uh
deconstructing yourself i think it's
like
also interesting to reconstruct various
selves you know
really interesting fun powerful useful
engaged selves right
that are seen to be completely md
um so it's a it's an
for me an evocative term and i just one
day started a blog like
um whimsically
because i wanted to say something that
day started a blog called deconstructing
yourself
deconstructing yourself and here we are
you know awesome
thank you so much michael for coming
we're we're at the hour
do you have any closing thoughts or
parting wisdom for us
my closing thought is that the calendar
invite said an hour and a half so i just
bought it
i just got it it did power in the day so
let's see
yeah excellent okay i mean if you want
to stick around
i don't there's no other events uh right
now so
if you're open to taking more questions
i am of course open to taking more
questions
let's do it okay i'm going to do a quick
just for anybody
you guys have more questions yeah just
for anybody who needs to take off i'm
going to do a quick little
uh closing spiel uh we have two
events coming up uh later today
one is concept unfolding with nicholas
benjamin
uh and that's where we play around with
uh
oops i sent that only to david that's
where we play around with
language and our uh
our ideas and we mix and match words
together at least that was what it was
like in the
first session this is the second session
he's the most interesting man at the
store i highly recommend it that's at 6
30 today
and then at 8 p.m we have internet
identity in our digital selves with
khalia young who is in bragg's
identity woman and lastly if you want to
see
more from the stoa or if you'd like to
support then you can check out
these links
and uh yeah we'll keep going for another
uh half hour or so with michael i
appreciate you taking the time michael
yeah you lost your time now that's right
it's an offering to the sangha
so excellent excellent okay
great so maybe uh
since there's not i don't think there's
any immediate
questions right now in the travis let's
assume that anyone who's willing to
stick around
uh is a little more into it so just do
it
just go for the weirder deeper more
awkward
yeah defense or more arcane questions
let's do it uh let me uh
there's none that are in the chat right
now and so maybe i'll try and think of
one we'll just take
anyone want to raise their hand katie
katie has her hand up i don't know if
this is weird deep arcane
enough but um i recently saw a talk by
by willoughby britain and she was
talking about when she first started
meditating what she was actually
training herself to do was to dissociate
um and she would think that was like a
really good meditation session if she
was really dissociated and then she was
talking about
how to recognize that in others and
so i'm wondering if you have thoughts on
how to recognize that in
oneself or in one's own practice or how
you kind of
um deal with students who are
going in that direction let's just use
the most basic definite
definition of dissociation which is you
can't feel your body
okay now it is the case that some
really deep ass meditations might
include that
um and it might be
a feature not a bug in those meditations
however if it's happening in your basic
meditation all the time it probably is a
pr
i would say that's a problem and so um
you recognize it by simply going i can't
feel my body
i'm dissociated and then you do
something like you know the cure is
as simple as it sounds like well now
just feel your feet feel your butt on
the chair or the cushion
feel your hands feel your body again
guess what you're no longer dissociated
i can't you know i don't have the the
level of psychic-ness to walk down the
street and just recognize
immediately who's dissociated and who's
not i mean
most people can a little bit recognize
that but i would say
the easiest way to recognize it in
another person is asking them
can you feel your body right now
and if they can't then it's like oh
you're dissociated let's
feel your body a little bit so i'm i'm
using a very very basic definition but
that
actually is you know pretty important
so um uh
i would i would it's not actually that
hard to detect or to cure now of course
if we're going to go into a really
deep genre part of the thing that
happens is you can't feel your body
right and it happens in a lot of other
practices too but at that point
you are doing something
[Music]
that is so um let's say uh
all consuming that
you're not dissociated by way of
distraction
or denial or avoidance or trying to get
away from something
you're you're just temporarily focused
on another
thing it can still cause issues maybe
but probably much less likely to
the kind of dissociation we're most
worried about is
you know using dissociation to
spiritually bypass
using dissociation to not notice when
you're being cruel to other people
and so on you know so
that's what i would say about that
and it is the case that lots people in
especially if you're
a new meditator and people haven't
really
warned you about this that it's really
easy to get into dissociation meditation
really fast and guess what if you've got
a lot of psychological issues
that might feel pretty damn good
and yet it is a problem so you want to
get
pulled back from that
easy to cure easy to notice thanks
yeah awesome uh evan you want to ask
your question
yeah so there's a more specific question
than the last one um
so in my own personal life in practice i
have found
that this sort of theoretical framework
for what cells are and how they are the
experience of them is generated provided
by
um people like yoshiback and thomas
medsinger
whom uh you've had on your uh
are in almost all respects like strictly
superior or
almost always superior theoretical
frameworks for understanding this stuff
as compared to the frameworks that we've
inherited
through the ancient wisdom traditions
they seemed to get most of the important
stuff that those
frameworks got right and also offered a
lot of additional sort of explanatory
power
and so that's sort of how my practice is
is it's a sort of
yeah sort of vajrayana practice but with
a yoshi box
thomas metzinger understanding of what's
going on and so
um i'm i'm wondering what your thoughts
are on this
how how um how much potential do you see
for
a more um you know neuroscientific
theoretical framework for uh
understanding the effects of meditation
practices and perhaps even you know
using that to teach or to come up with
new sets of practices that might be
extraordinarily effective
in short that's super fascinating right
there's a lot there
um obviously there's a reason i had
thomas
metzinger and yoshua bach on
the show i you know love those guys i
know those people
they're wonderful to talk to i had a
long long long
relationship with tomas and you know
these frameworks are incredibly helpful
they're um they don't have exactly the
same framework but
you know like thinking that way about
what a self
is is incredibly helpful it's clarifying
um it's useful for your practice it
might be useful for developing new
practices it's helped me in my practice
etc etc etc and
there's important stuff that they're not
talking about
for example you know um
[Music]
i don't see maybe yoshi does but i
definitely haven't seen thomas talking
about
you know the multiple selves
or generation of new um
you know the the yadam practice like
generating
a new powerful effective self
what how that works and why that's
interesting
so there's a lot of stuff that's being
left out
um and one of the things beyond what the
ones i just mentioned
that is even more left out is just the
fact that
you know we all know reductive models
are really helpful at clarifying
but they leave
dimensions out and so i'm always
leaving one foot out of that uh
at least one foot out of the
neuroscientific pile
saying a lot more is probably going on
in there
than what that model covers i'm using
the model because
it's so helpful and it's you know we've
got traditional models and then we've
got this
neuroscientific model by triangulating
we can get a lot out of it etc etc but
i'm very very very concerned
that people don't just eat that whole
hog and say that's the one true model
because it's not and it's not like it
even exists somewhere
as a you know fully fleshed out
and chrome plated here's the model you
know
these are just ideas they're super
helpful
they interact with traditional ideas in
really fruitful ways
but i found myself after
really going there for like 10 years
now backing up and kind of okay
there was thesis antithesis let's start
looking at more
synthesis where i'm able to bring back
in some of the traditional stuff
and and um
not just think of it all as
um you know piles of neurons
interacting so i would say i love that
stuff
and there's more
everyone should be fluent in it though
if they're gonna do this
meditation type thing in a serious way
over a long period of time
awesome any follow-up seven
um thanks for those thoughts yeah my one
follow-up would be i i just do
think that um that with uh especially
yoshi's type of models he very much
gets into the sort of generation of
perhaps what we could consider the sub
personalities and the um
the you know things you could use for
you to practice for example um
and i i was just curious about your
thoughts of like do you know anyone or
are you familiar with anyone who's doing
work say like using some of the perhaps
slightly more
scientifically or you know grounded in
neuroscience
models of say the way the brain regions
communicate to each other and generate
emergent properties and you know the
stuff that the guys over at quality of
computing are doing and so on to like
create
um you know sort of more effective vajra
inflected
practices because that's the sort of
thing i'm very interested in
um the field is wide open at this point
i'm playing around with that
i know that um a lot kelly is playing
around with that there's a couple people
who are
trying to uh develop
um i think uh i think rinzen is
playing around with that some um
so there's there's various people and
we're all talking to each other so it's
you know it's
uh it's a wide open field and it's
really
interesting and cool and important
there's a whole way to
take stuff like jungian active
imagination
and internal family systems therapy
and parts work and a couple things like
that
and start mixing them together with
something like ishta david to practice
or diet yoga or whatever
[Music]
that is really interesting and seems to
have a lot of
really powerful applications but that so
far is kind of still in the
developmental stage
i've been doing some of this and
teaching some of it live but i'm very
you know quick to admit like
hey this you want to come and try this
out let's try it out but
we're just experimenting right now
thank you and if anyone knows of anyone
else really working in that direction
i'd love to hear about them
uh anjin do you want to ask a question
hey michael um i
i found the most helpful aspect of my
personal life of kind of really trying
to put the model of
that you aren't just one self that you
have multiple selves into practices my
relationship to emotions
um i i felt like there was a huge
improvement in my life when i realized
the same way i don't need to
scratch my nose when i feel that it when
i
feel that anger it's a suggestion it's
not me
that my emotions are just things
that are part of me and their tools and
this i'm curious if there's other
dimensions
to life that practically change as well
your relationship to them with this
model of having multiple selves
other than emotions yeah
and i would say um in the way i'm
looking at it it's not just a model of
multiple cells it's a model
of we could say no self
multiple selves different kinds of cells
it's even bigger than what you're
describing um
emptiness but
if we back up and just say multiple
cells it affects every part of life
because
you're bringing that multiplicity to
everything
that you do right so it's helpful in
emotions
it's helpful in decision making it's
helpful in interacting with other human
beings it's helpful in understanding
how to navigate your own experience
it's helpful to um start getting
a more integrated sort of feeling within
as we
work with kind of um negotiating between
these different
sort of clumps of thought and feeling
it's massively applicable
basically and it's very important at the
same time to
understand that none of those are the
real you
you know they're they're interesting
aspects of what can come up
so um i would just say even if you go
into this in a completely psychological
way like a non-meditative just
psychological take
it's still super it's unbelievably
helpful
um but when we go there uh
both psychologically and informed by
meditation
informed by uh nonduality even
um it becomes uh radically
helpful uh spiritually and
um in our i would say
for the world you know we can really
start to show up in a different way
do any examples come to mind in the
realm of decision making
um
anytime you're going to make a decision
it's not a decision unless there are at
least two parts that are negotiating
otherwise it's not a decision right
so um if there's just
one part then you already know what
you're doing so
in other words you're going to start
evaluating we always think of it as one
self evaluating two sides but
it's much easier to understand as two
different
sides that are talking to each other and
so
if we allow that discussion to kind of
unfold in a more conscious manner like
if it was this if if this way
if decision a could talk it would talk
like this decision b could talk it would
talk like that
and just allow that dialogue to happen
in imagination
this is extremely helpful and actually
unpacks a lot of stuff about the
decision that was hidden
you know and furthermore it will sort of
decide itself at that point
if you go back and forth with that
process the decision
emerges and it's very hard to say
where it came from you know except via
dialogue
so that would that's the example i would
give and of course we can do that with
decisions with many more than two
choices
to be greedy at the cup um do you have
examples for
relationality um
when you say relationality what do you
which specific thing do you mean
um you mentioned relationships i did
um it's again these are really broad
topics but let's say
um uh you're in your partner just said
something
and you and one part of you is like
they're absolutely right
uh and they have every right to ask for
that and another part of you is like
you you i hate when
you ask for that
now you're having two internal reactions
to the same event
and um i know no one besides me
has ever had that experience um
and which one is supposed to respond and
what's the other one supposed to do just
suck on it i mean it's it's really a um
[Music]
it's an interesting i think it's
fascinating every time something like
that happens it's
it's beautiful and interesting but it's
also
has a conundrum aspect or a koan aspect
right
and so there's you know now it starts
branching into ways to talk about it one
thing is that internally we do a
negotiation
and see what response wants to come
forward
or you know we do it all in in dialogue
maybe the person is used to us having
more than one response
you know there's a lot of ways it could
work but all of them are fascinating and
all of them are truer
than just landing on one response
and leaving the other one completely out
that's how we get into suppression and
denial and a bunch of like
you know squashed rage that then comes
out inappropriately
when they burp or something hey you
burped
and really it's just the leftover anger
that you squashed before
so you know you'll notice
that for all kinds of external
experience
we have more than one response arising
and that
that's how it applies that's why i say
this comes up
in every situation almost
and it's also very important of course
to realize that
if it's thoughts and feelings you know
as far as i'm concerned
none of that is a is really you i mean
those are just sub personalities
and the real you if there is such a
thing is outside of thought and feeling
entirely
you know it is simply awareness and even
that is empty so we can just drill down
and drill down and drill down
so yeah it's
let's say wildly applicable to life
in ways that are really really
interesting and helpful
awesome thanks michael uh pranam
has it what's up
you know this is where uh this kind of
um synthetic or
that's the wrong word and newly created
deity yoga type practices can come in
because it's possible to then
once we understand that there's multiple
possible selves and that none of them
are really
us you can generate new ones on purpose
they're just certain agglomerations of
thought and feeling
and and then actually
some of those are better responders to
certain situations
right they're specifically developed for
certain situations and that can be
really really interesting other times
it's better to just sink into the muck
and see what's really going on
and just engage with life as it is with
all these different
seemingly sub personalities come up it's
all fun and interesting
that uh also dovetails very nice so the
products
next question which is about dark paths
do you wanna yeah for sure
so this kind of goes back to uh
a little bit earlier in the talk where
you know we talked about
the accessibility of all these really
intense teachings
you have the greatest last name you know
thank you i only recently learned about
it
only the recently what only recently
kind of learned the
sanskrit mind and everything yeah no i
had to like memorize
that word 40 years ago right nice
very nice yeah anyway go ahead yeah
and with all these really intense
teachings coming up um
and the fact that they're more
accessible than ever how do
you envision supporting people who are
going through
difficult times through meditation say
kind of like to katie's question that
associated experiences
um particularly if you don't have a
teacher
or a sangha
well if you don't have a teacher or a
sangha you know you're
um you should get a sangha at least to
get
at least one other person you're talking
to you know
um doing it all alone is
real difficult and more likely to lead
to difficulty
right whereas if we're in relationship
with others
it can really help um
uh but what i would say is that
i always have people checking the basics
all the time in their meditation and i
don't mean the meditation basics i mean
the life basics like how's your sleep
how's your eating how's your exercise
how's your friendship how's your
relationship
you know and if any of those are getting
way out of whack
it's time to check in with yourself
about it and check with
in with others about it um depending on
how you know bad it's getting but
these things go awry they're like early
warning signs
they go a little bit off long before
anything
big happens you know you're gonna start
seeing
well yeah i had a psychotic break and
then you start asking them questions and
it's like but a month earlier i stopped
eating and sleeping you know
it's like yeah there we go you know
that's
that's where it started to be obvious
that something was missed so you want to
check these very simple life basics and
it's not like if one of them is off it's
a big
problem but you know if something
changes
maybe you want to you know just be aware
of that and look into it
beyond that um it gets really hairy
really fast some stuff is for medical
doctors some stuff is for psychiatrists
some stuff is for
garden variety variety therapists
some stuff is just probably you can work
it out talking to a friend some stuff
you must talk to your meditation teacher
and knowing the difference is hard
and you know i work with a couple people
who have
you know major difficulties psychotic
breaks and so on that they've gone
through
not necessarily because of their
meditation or whatever but just for life
and uh you know most of them are are
kind of like
um layered up in or
doctored up like they're they've got a
you know regular therapist they've got a
psychiatrist
they're talking to me they're talking to
a life coach to kind of keep everything
in balance and it works if you can
afford it
you know in other words the more
help you get the more types of help
you know it's
prudent and also different people are
good at
curing or preventing different kinds of
disruption
but i would say on your own that's a
great reason to have
friends and family who are informed
friends
who are practitioners also who know what
you're doing
maybe some kind of teacher that you can
talk to
and then usually if your work if you
think your problem is coming from
spiritual practice
if they're if the teacher is any good at
all they'll be like
they'll know whether it's coming from
the practice or you need to go see a
therapist
or at least they'll have a guess
thank you yeah travis do you have time
for a follow-up
uh sure yeah cool and kind of in that
line of you know best practices for
beginners
going with that whole line of
personalized meditation you were talking
about
in the beginning um how do you see that
how do you see that manifesting um
in terms of like discovery i know zach
had a question about committing to a
practice
um so yeah how do you think that
teachers
could change their approach or beginners
to change their approach and
discovering different practices on mix
and matching techniques between
different languages and schools and then
um i mean just start out by
this is what's good everything's
available to try you know so
get on an app or five different apps or
get on youtube and just try a bunch of
beginner techniques
and see what resonates for you
and now now do that while continuing to
learn about it go a little deeper but
it's very traditional that people shop
around
for a long time before they deeply
commit to one teacher or deeply commit
to one practice
and i strongly encourage that because
it's
very much the case that
what you know the beginning practice
that works for someone else
probably won't work for you you know
it's just
there's like a wide variation
and so try some out and then uh
you know give it your all for a while
and then see where
the direction you're going in because
oftentimes
once you kind of get your feet on the
ground with one practice some of these
other ones suddenly become
way easier so
so just literally try a bunch out for
five minutes and see what it's like
and then and then start going from there
being like it's you now there's no
excuse for not being fully informed
you gotta at least try some different
stuff out
you know maybe not like blood sacrifice
current journal ground rituals at first
but not to begin with but
you know everything else is easily easy
to try out and i
encourage you to do that
thanks yeah
it looks like we're at time michael
would you like to make an actual closing
thought now or a
part some parting well my closing
thought is that the the fact that this
is even occurring the stowaway is
occurring
and stuff like evolving ground is
occurring i just love it i love it love
it love stuff like
sfdc is occurring san francisco dharma
collective
it's a new world and i'm so into it
and i'm so glad it's happening and it's
just kind of
opening all these musty doors that i
always wanted opened you know it's like
oh we get to now just didn't
talk about all that openly thank god
and um so thank you for coming and
asking me questions
and continue to do this a lot it's
a big um
opportunity that that i really
appreciate so i can
tag with a compliment i found this an
especially strong and
endearing format for you michael
i i would encourage you it's part of my
marketing plan to be a dairy
thanks a lot thank you david i
appreciate it
thank you for coming and speaking of us
this michael we
really appreciate your presence here
much meta so have a good one
all right bye bye
thank you